<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of charity mistaken; or, some reasons against committees forcing the Parliaments godly, faithfull and plundered ministers (who labor in the Word and doctrine) to pay fifth parts to sequestred wives and children. With some answers to some arguments alledged for it. As also some complaints of poore plundered ministers, against the hard dealings of some committees about fifth parts, and juries, with a motion for their settlements for their lives.</title>
            <author>Williamson, R., fl. 1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E723_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207250</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866315</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 111:E723[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of charity mistaken; or, some reasons against committees forcing the Parliaments godly, faithfull and plundered ministers (who labor in the Word and doctrine) to pay fifth parts to sequestred wives and children. With some answers to some arguments alledged for it. As also some complaints of poore plundered ministers, against the hard dealings of some committees about fifth parts, and juries, with a motion for their settlements for their lives.</title>
                  <author>Williamson, R., fl. 1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the desire of a friend, and are to bee sold at the Three Bibles in Pauls Church-yard, and in Westminster-hall.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654. [i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed p. 16: R. Williamson.</note>
                  <note>Thomason recieved his copy in Decmeber 1653.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb:"; 4 in imprint date crossed out and "3" written in.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166773:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcovery of Charity Miſtaken; OR, Some Reaſons againſt Committees forcing the Parliaments godly, faithfull and plundered Miniſters (who labor in the Word and Doctrine) to pay fifth parts to Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred Miniſters Wives and Children. With ſome Anſwers to ſome Arguments Alledged for it. AS ALSO Some Complaints of poore plundered Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, againſt the hard dealings of ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees about fifth parts, and Juries, with a motion for their ſettlements for their Lives.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 5.17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Let the Elders that rule well, bee counted worthy of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſpecially they who labour in the word and Doctrine, for the Scripture ſaith, thou ſhalt not muzzle the Oxe that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the corn, and the Labourer is worthy of his reward.</q>
            </q>
            <q>Omne beneficium poſtulat Officium.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed at the deſire of a Friend, and are to bee ſold at the Three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and in <hi>Weſtminster</hi>-hall. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166773:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166773:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of Charity miſtaken.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received your Letter, wherein you deſire to know my reaſons, why fifth parts ſhould not be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Wives and Children of ſequeſtred Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, by thoſe Miniſters that are put into Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, (which with ſome intermixed grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) I hereby humbly offer to your ſerious conſideration, and candid interpretation. But to prevent miſtakes I premiſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That I plead not againſt the States allowing fifth parts to the Wives and Children of ſequeſtred Delinquents temporall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, except they be Offices into which others are put: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p n="2">2 Do I intend any evill, but good, to thoſe that have ſate, and do now ſit at the ſtern of our Commonwealth; (I am one of thoſe that have acted with, and ſuffered much, in name, body and eſtate for them) but that you may ſee, lament, and reforme the hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that ſome of their beſt friends have received, at the hands of ſome of their Committees, and worſe may, if ſome good courſe be not ſpeedily taken to reforme and reſtraine them; and therefore I hope, that neither you nor any others wel-affected, will take in ill part what I ſhall ſay in vindication of this Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is not warrantable for Committees to force poor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Ministers, put into Sequeſtrations, to pay fifth parts of the profits of them, to the reſpective Wives and Children of Ministers, that are ſequeſtred from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And my Arguments to prove it are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe they have no right unto them, for if they have any right to them, it is either in right of the ſequeſtred Miniſters, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166773:3"/>of themſelves, but neither of theſe waies, therefore no way.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Not in right of ſequeſtred Miniſters, becauſe they have no right unto them, they had (it may be) a civill right unto them, but that they have loſt by their convicted ſcandalouſneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency, and are dead in Law, now (you know) when a Miniſter is dead, neither he, nor his Wife, nor Children have any right to any profits due after his death, and therefore not to a fifth part.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But you will ſay, they are not dead in law, becauſe not legally put out, by a Judge at Common Law, or deprived by their Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> I Anſwer, 1 They are deſervedly put out by the Authority of the higheſt Judicature in <hi>England,</hi> for moſt have been ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the late Committee for releife of plundered Miniſters, who were all Parliament-men; and though ſome have been ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by Country Committees, (who commonly Favoured De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linqent and ſcandalous Miniſters, much more then the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Plundered Miniſters did) you know theſe Committees were authorized to do what they did, who proceeded as favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably as they could, according to thoſe Rules given them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> the ſcandalouſneſſe and delinquency alleadged and proved againſt them; if not (as I have heard) they had their appeale even to the houſe it ſelfe, if made within halfe a year after ſequeſtration,</p>
            <p n="2">2 You know that Juries are for the moſt part malignant and corrupt, favourers of malignant, and ſcandalous Miniſters, and foreſwore taking upon them to bring in their Verdict not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the evidence, but to judge of the Law it ſelfe; So that if ſome good courſe be not ſpeedily taken, Acts of Parliament, and mens proprieties will be little or nothing worth. I am confident there are no greater oppreſſions in <hi>England,</hi> then malignant and corrupted Juries are to honeſt men; and yet (though the Lives and Eſtates of Godly and Wel-affected men are to be tryed by them) there is no proviſion made againſt them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And beſides the fifth part is commonly allowed to the wives and children of thoſe Miniſters, who would undoubtedly have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, not onely by an honeſt wel-affected, and uncorrupted Jury at Common-Law, but by a Vote of the major part of the whole Houſe it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166773:3"/>
            <p n="4">4 And truely, many (if not moſt) of thoſe that now ſtand ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, were never legally, (if we take legally, according to Gods holy Word) put in, for God never ſent them; For he never ſends any but ſuch as he quallifies with gifts of Illumination and Sanctification con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and neceſſary for them, both which many (if not moſt) of them wanted, when they were firſt ſent by men.</p>
            <p n="5">5 And truely, many of thoſe Patrons that preſented them, as well as thoſe Biſhops that inſtituted them, were as ſequeſtrable for delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency and ſcandall as themſelves, and therefore ſure they were not fit and competent Judges of them and their behaviour. But to leave this to the Parliament, who know upon what good grounds they have ſequeſtred them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I ſay they have no right in themſelves to fifth parts. For 1. Though it be ſaid by ſome that the Parliament hath given them to them, and therefore, that they have as much right to fifth parts, as the Miniſters put into ſequeſtrations have to the four parts: The Parliament ſeeing how forward ſome were to cut ſuch large thongs out of honeſt mens, their good friends, ſides (if I may ſo ſpeak) as to allow third parts to the ſequeſtred Miniſters under the colour of their Wives and Children, did, as in the caſe of Uſury, make a Law to reſtrain them to fifth parts; and thereby did indeed tollerate, but not command their Inferiors, nor neceſſitate themſelves to allow fifth parts from poor plundered Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which Law of theirs, is (God knows) much abuſed by their Committees, to their great diſhonor, and the grief and undoing of many godly Miniſters and their Families, and the maintaining and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of their irreconcilable Enemies. Secondly, I deny the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For it doth not follow, that becauſe the State doth tollerate and reſtraine Uſury to 6 <hi>l. per cent.</hi> that therefore it is lawful and juſt; So neither doth it follow, becauſe the State doth tollerate a maintenance to the wives and children of ſequeſtred Miniſters out of thoſe Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations where godly and plundered Miniſters are placed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain their Agents to fifth parts, that therefore it is lawful to force them to pay them to them.</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>You will ſay it is lawful by mans Law, though (it may be) it is not lawful by Gods Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Sir, Grant the latter and you muſt yeeld the former, for mans Law muſt be rightly grounded upon Gods, elſe it will not be a righteous but ungodly Law. But more of this hereafter. For Anſwer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166773:4"/>I ſay, with ſubmiſſion to all in Authority, that they have no right unto fifth parts by Mans Law, for</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Parliament did not command, but only tollerate fifth parts, as it doth not follow, that becauſe our ſtate doth tollerate men to take 6 l. <hi>per cent.</hi> that therefore they muſt take ſo much, for men may lend for leſſe; or freely for nothing if they will. But Committees force poor plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters to pay them to the Wives and Children of ſequeſtred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, though people pay them not their Tythes and Dues.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Their Committees are Patrons <hi>pro tempore</hi> of all ſequeſtred Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, to which they preſent their Miniſters when they ſend them to the Aſſembly, or other godly Orthodox Divines, and inſtitute and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them, when they give them Orders for their reſpective places; now by that good old unrepealed Law againſt Symonie; it is unlawful for any Patron, when he preſents any Miniſter to a preſentative Living, to reſerve a fifth part, yea, any part of the profits of the ſame, either for himſelfe or any others (be they never ſo poor) as all skilled in our Laws, know right well; and therefore I conclude, that it is not lawfull for Committees to force poor plundered Miniſters, to pay to the wives and children of thoſe that have been ſequeſtred, a full fifth part of the profits of their Livings, as they doe, under the penalties of Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or impriſonment.</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>But you will ſay, that every inferior Patron is, but Committees are not, tyed to that Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Sir, I profeſs I am very loath to write any thing that may be by any conſtrued againſt the late Parliaments juſt proceedings but I hope I may do this without offence, as wel as others write againſt Uſury which is tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated by them. Therefore in anſwer I ſay, That it is contrary to the late Parliaments Declarations; For, you know, the late Parliament Declared and Promiſed to repaire the loſſes of thoſe that were plundered for their adhering to them, which this forcing of them to pay fifth parts doth not doe, but (I will not ſay) plunder them more. And alſo to maintaine the good and wholeſome Laws of our Land, of which kind that known Law againſt Symonie is one, and as yet is not formally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, but even by the Parliament and Judges juſtly puniſhed; now to force Miniſters to pay fifth parts to the Wives and Children of them that are ſequeſtred, hath the materiality, if not the whole formality of Symonie; And beſides, you know that Committees are not ſupream but ſubordinate Patrons, and therefore are bound to obſerve the Laws of our Land as wel as any others.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166773:4"/>
            <p>Second Argument, To force poor plundered Miniſters to pay fifth parts to the Wives and Children of ſequeſtred Miniſters, is contrary to their proceedings, with others in like caſes. For</p>
            <p n="1">1 Many men have been ſequeſtred from Offices of great profit, which they or their friends have bought with great ſums of mony, and which they did and might hold by the Laws of the Land as well as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and yet Committees though they have continued thoſe Offices, and put others, though not plundered, into them; yet have not enjoyned, much leſſe forced them to pay fifth parts to their Wives and children, though they were poor and had nothing elſe to live upon but their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which was never yet denied to the Wives and Children of ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Yea, many Heads and Officers of Colledges and Halls in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, have been ſequeſtred from their ſeveral Headſhips and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and yet have not forced thoſe that have been put into them to pay their Wives and Children fifth parts, though ſome of them have neither Wife nor Children, neither have they been plundered as ſome Miniſters (that are forced to pay fifth parts) have been, neither are they defrauded of, and troubled about their dues, as many poor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Country Miniſters commonly are. I write not this out of any envy of them, God knows my heart, I wiſh them better then they have, for ſome of them have too little, but to let you ſee the inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſome Committees proceedings. Yet why both theſe ſorts of men ſhould be exempted from fifth parts, and other godly and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Miniſters who have Wives and Children of their own ſhould be charged with them, I ſee no reaſon at all, but only will.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is inconvenient to force them thereunto in many reſpects;</p>
            <p n="1">1 To Committees, for there by they are many times put to a great deal of labor and charge, to watch and wait to make orders, and hear cauſes about fifth parts, which might well be ſpared, and better ſpent.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To the Parliament and Army. For 1. Thereby godly Miniſters having been plundered for aiding of them, are diſabled now to helpe them as formerly they have, and might, and would. 2. Malignants are not thereby made their friends, but the more able to hurt them, and their friends, and doubtleſſe will when time ſerveth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To their Miniſters, and that many ways, for it takes them off from their ſtudies, compels them to be abſent from their Families, and flocks, and puts them to great trouble, labor, and charges to attend the hearing of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166773:5"/>their Cauſes. For many times they are put off until their friends be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and a Committee made againſt them; yea, when they have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good cauſe, and that approved of, and have been thereupon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from fifth parts, yet many times they have been charged again, and hereby they are not only diſabled from repairing their old dilapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated houſes, and releiving the poor; but are neceſſitated to be more ſtrict with their Pariſhioners about their Tythes and Taxes then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would be. Yea, further, it animates malignants againſt them, for they look upon fifth parts as an earneſt that their old ſequeſtred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters have right to all, and ſhall one day enjoy all again; and this makes them many times, and wayes, to vex and oppreſſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments poor plundered Miniſters, by over-valuing, and over-taxing their Livings, that a fifth part is made a third part, and then there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains but two parts to the Parliaments poor plundered Miniſters, to maintain themſelves, their own Wives and Children, pay Taxes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive the poor, repair their houſes, and keep hoſpitality; and it may be are forced to goe to law with their Pariſhioners for all, and in the mean time borrow mony to pay taxes and fifth parts, and in the end compound for halfe the value of their Tythes, after they have ſpent twiſe as much as their Tythes were worth. Is this the way to releive poore plundered Miniſters? Yea, further, it being left to ſequeſtred Miniſters Wives and Children to chuſe their fifth parts of which Living they pleaſe (for many of them had two Livings, ſome three) it ſo fals out, that they commonly pitch upon the places where poor plundered Miniſters are placed, and let the other alone, or make ſome under-hand bargain with them, and ſo it comes to paſſe, that many times godly Miniſters, who have been deprived of the lives of their friends, of their eſtates in the wars, and have Wives and many ſmall Children of their own, and friends, who have loſt their limbs in the Parliaments Service to maintaine, are compelled to pay full fifth parts unto the Wife or child of the ſequeſtred, that hath it may be good conſiderable temporall eſtate to live upon, and this without defalcation of taxes and charges, which were or are in many places above a fourth part of the whole; but this is occaſioned by Committees giving them leave to chuſe where they liſt, and alwaies, and all of one, and ſo Newters, yea, Malignants till of late, and young men, who have either none; or but little charge, and never loſt any thing by the wars, eſcape fifth-part-free, and the burthen, as hath been ſhewed, is laid upon the aged wel-affected, poor plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters, who have great charge of children and friends depending upon them.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166773:5"/>
            <p>Third Argument, To force poor plundered Miniſters, put into Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations, to pay fifth parts unto the wives and children of ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred Miniſters, is a practiſe not well grounded upon the Holy word of God, which ought to be the rule and foundation of Chriſtian mens actions. Therefore it is not warrantable. — I know it is pretended to be an act of great mercy, and the Miniſters that are againſt fifth parts (though they be truely godly and poor, and merciful to thoſe that are poor indeed) are hardly cenſuRed, and looked upon, as covetous, ſelfe-lovers, and without natural affection; but it is for the moſt part by ſuch that are ſo indeed, and alſo falſe accuſers, and deſpiſers of thoſe that are truely good (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.) But Sir, ſome wiſe and worthy men ſay, it was but an act of humane pollicy deviſed at firſt by ſome in favor of Malignants, and connived at by others (as in time of the wars) favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honeſt godly Miniſters, but continued to their undoing. Now to evidence it to be a practiſe not well grounded upon the Word of God, I ſuppoſe it will not be amiſſe to lay down thoſe portions of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture producible for the lawfulneſſe of Committees forcing fifth parts from godly, poor plundered Miniſters, to the wives and children of thoſe Miniſters that are ſequeſtred by the Parliaments Authority, and then clear them.</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>Firſt is or may be alleadged,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.26. And unto <hi>Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the Prieſt, ſaid the King, get thee to <hi>Anathoth</hi> unto thine owne fields, for thou art worthy of death. <hi>Hereupon it is ſaid that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that though</hi> Solomon <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> Abiather <hi>the Prieſt from being Prieſt unto the Lord, yet he did not take away all his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from him, but commanded him to goe to</hi> Anathoth <hi>to his owne fields there, therefore ſay they, fifth parts are grounded upon the Word of God, for here is example for a maintenance out of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred Miniſters own fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> For Anſwer unto this, be pleaſed to conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That <hi>Solomon</hi> was an abſolute King as moſt men hold, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily made by the Lord, as <hi>Adonijah</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.15. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Solomons</hi> practiſe is no good preſident for our Committees, who are but conditional, elſe we are in a worſe condition then wee were in formerly, but let it goe for good, then know</p>
            <p n="2">2 That <hi>Solomon</hi> (the Supream Magiſtrate) ſequeſtred <hi>Abiather</hi> the High Prieſt, as a grand Delinquent for adhering to <hi>Adonijah,</hi> who would needs be King before King <hi>David</hi> was dead, or willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166773:6"/>his Kingdome into his hand, for which <hi>Solomon</hi> judged him worthy of death, and yet pardoned him as to life, and temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and confined him to his fields at <hi>Anathoth,</hi> which belonged not to him as he was High Prieſt, if <hi>Solomons</hi> practiſe be a good preſident for fifth parts, why not for our Committees to ſequeſter.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That <hi>Solomon</hi> pardoned <hi>Abiather</hi> as to life and temporal eſtate, for that time, for his former good Service done to his father <hi>David,</hi> and ſufferings, for and with him, but thruſt him out of the Prieſts Office and confined him to his own fields at <hi>Anathoth;</hi> So many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters though they have more deſerved death then <hi>Abiather</hi> did, yet have been pardoned by the Parliament, as to life and liberty, though they have done both them and their Fathers, and friends, all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife they could. But now that Committees practiſe in allowing fifth parts to ſequeſtred Miniſters Wives and Children, and forcing godly poor plundered Miniſters to pay them, is not well grounded upon <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons,</hi> nor conſonant thereunto, is manifeſt. For</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Solomon</hi> ſequeſtred <hi>Abiather</hi> from being Prieſt before the Lord, and put <hi>Zadock</hi> in his room, but he did not allot <hi>Abiather</hi> or his wife or children a fifth part of the High Prieſts maintenance, and much leſſe compell <hi>Zadock,</hi> who performed the Office to pay it him or any other; But now Committees doe commonly cut out fifth parts as large as third parts of the profits of ſequeſtred Livings, to ſequeſtred Miniſters wives and children, and conſtrain godly, faithful, plundered <hi>Zadockes</hi> to pay them (beſides performing the Office, to which by the Law of God and man they have ever been annexed and paying of all taxes and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges impoſed, which <hi>Zadock</hi> knew not of.) under the penalties of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration or impriſonment, to ſequeſtred <hi>Abiathers</hi> ſhall I ſay? that name is not convient, for they never bear the Arke before, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing with, or for the Parliament, but rather acted with <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and either like <hi>Doeg</hi> murdered, or at leſt, like <hi>Shimei</hi> curſed, and railed, and caſt ſtones againſt them, and their friends, now whether moſt Committee-men have truly written after <hi>Solomons</hi> copy, let all ſeeing and uncorrupted men judge,</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Solomon</hi> did confine <hi>Abiather</hi> to his own fields or poſſeſſions at <hi>Anathoth,</hi> for near thereunto was the City of <hi>Nob</hi> before <hi>Saul</hi> deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, where <hi>Abiathers</hi> land lay, as the learned
<note place="margin">* S. <hi>W. R.</hi>
               </note> Knight obſerves. He did not give him leave to make away his temporall eſtate, and then chuſe his maintenance where and when he would out of <hi>Zadocks</hi> (as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166773:6"/>ſome Committees have done) no, but he confined him to his owne fields belonging to his Perſon, not to his Office, and that was a ſpeciall act of grace to <hi>Abiather,</hi> becauſe he had carryed the Ark of the Lord before his father <hi>David,</hi> and had been afflicted in all wherein his father <hi>David</hi> had been afflicted. And truely, if we look back to the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.22. chapters, we ſhal find that <hi>Abiather</hi> deſerved ſome favor, more then other. For he had done, and ſuffered much, he had born the Ark before <hi>David,</hi> and he had loſt his Father, and friends, and moveable goods for <hi>Davids</hi> ſake, and ſhared with him in all his troubles, and his fault was ſuch as a wiſer man might have ſlipt into; For <hi>Adonijah</hi> was the Kings eldeſt Son, a proper man, and <hi>Davids</hi> Darling, and the King had not declared any thing againſt <hi>Adonijahs</hi> ſucceeding him. And <hi>Joab</hi> (a wiſe and valiant man) the Kings General was alſo in the action; and theſe things, no doubt, if <hi>Abiather</hi> did not plead, <hi>Solomon</hi> (being a wiſe man) knew right well and alſo that this was the firſt time, that ever he was found faulty, and therefore he gracioufly pardoned him as to life and temporals, and only ſequeſtred him from the Office and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the High Prieſt, both which he deſervedly, freely, and fully gave to <hi>Zadock,</hi> who had faithfully adhered to his father <hi>David</hi> and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Indeed Sir, thoſe <hi>Abiathars</hi> that acted with, and ſuffered for the Parliament in the beginnings of our late troubles and changes, but failed (it may be, inconſiderately ſome of them) in the matter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donijah,</hi> might very well plead this practice of <hi>Solomon,</hi> as a good prefident for our wiſe Sages and Committees to follow: But why cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Shimei's,</hi> and ſeditious <hi>Korah's,</hi> who have done what they could (and they are moſt of them the ſame they were) to ſubdue and deſtroy the Parliament and their adherents, ſhould be permitted to plead this for themſelves, their wives or children, eſpecially againſt godly <hi>Zadocks</hi> who have faithfully adhered to, and conſtantly ſerved the Parliament even in their greateſt extremities, and ſuffered ſo much for them. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I ſee no reaſon at all.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>The next place that is brought for fifth parts, is Mat.</hi> 5.5. Bleſſed are the mercifull for they ſhall finde mercy: <hi>therefore ſeeing poor plundered Ministers will not of their owne accord give the wives and children of ſequeſtred Miniſters fifth parts, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Committees to force them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To this I might anſwer thus; that they muſt ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That to give fifth parts is a duty.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:166773:7"/>
            <p n="2">2 That they are able to doe it, or elſe I beleeve they will not be bleſſed in their deed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By way of queſtion <hi>ad homines,</hi> pray what fifth parts do theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful men allow to thoſe Biſhops, &amp;c. whoſe onely crime was, that they were Biſhops, whoſe Lands and Poſſeſſions they have bought (for a ſmal matter yea, as ſome ſay) for a fifth part of the worth of them, and do they not appear ſo merciful to Malignants of purpoſe that they may ſpeak well of them, or that they may obtain mercy from them if the times ſhould alter, which they fear, and ſo is not all their ſpecious ſhew of Charity to others, any other thing then plain ſelfe-love? I do not know their hearts (but God doth) and therefore I do but ask the queſtion.</p>
            <p n="4">4 But I anſwer, <hi>ad rem,</hi> to the thing objected, and inſinuated.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That thoſe for whom they ſo ſtifly plead, and violently act, are not commonly ſuch ſubjects of miſery, and therefore not ſuch objects of mercy, as they would make the world beleeve they are: For I know it is often pretended that there is a Wife and ten or twelve ſmall Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like to periſh if they be not releived by a fifth part of a poor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Miniſters maintenance, but upon due examination there is found neither Wife nor Children but onely one ſingle Son or Daughter, and either of them eighteen or twenty yeares of age, and well bred up, and provided for, and able to get their Livings, and maintained in their Silks and Sattens. Now let conſcience ſpeake whether it be the mercy here intended by our Savior to compell a poor plundered Miniſter (who hath really a Wife, and it may be eight or ten or twelve ſmal children unable to help themſelves) to pay a full fifth out of the profits of his Living, for which he labours night and day to ſuch a ſingle perſon or perſons who are well able to get their livelihoods by their labor, if they had not friends to help them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I ſay that the mercy to which bleſſedneſſe is promiſed is ſpiritual, and hath for its originall the Holy Spirit of God,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10. Dr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice in loc.</hi>
               </note> for its ſubject a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall regenerated man, and for its cheife object, ſpiritual men (I mean ſpirituall, in oppoſition to carnal) and for its ends, ſpiritual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives: Now whether this be ſuch a ſpiritual mercy, let ſpiritual men judge.</p>
            <p n="3">3 True ſpirituall mercy is guided by the true rule of juſtice, ſo that he that doth not regulate his actions by it, is not to be reputed a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually mercifull man, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 112.4.5: a good man is righteous as well as merciful: Now whether this forcing of poor plundered Miniſters
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166773:7"/>to pay fifth parts to ſequeſtred Miniſters wives and children be an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on guided by the rules of true juſtice, let all juſt men judge. The Word of God, which ought to be the rule of Juſtice, ſaith plainly, <hi>That he that preacheth the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 14. And <hi>the laborer is worthy of his hyer,</hi> Luk. 10 7. And <hi>if any will not work they muſt not eate,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. And <hi>let the Elder that rules wel be counted worthy of double honour, eſpecially they who labour in the Word and Doctrine;</hi> For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne, and the laborer is worthy of his reward,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 17, 18. But now doth not this forcing of poor plundered Miniſters to pay fifth parts, make them unable to live of the Goſpel? and a Goſpell maintenance ought to be more liberal and large then that before or under the Law; <hi>Becauſe the ministration of the Goſpell is more excellent then that before or under the Law,</hi> Heb. 8.6. but fifth parts make it much leſſe, yea, then it was in times of Popery; they deprive the labourer of his hire and reward, and of that double, yea, ſingle honor which is due unto him; they muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne, that gives their bread to them, that labor not for it. And if that remarkable Poſition of many learned and unbyaſſed men (Miniſters and others) be true, as they boldly affirm, and ſtrongly prove) that Tythes were alwayes paid to Chriſt, as they gather from, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5, to 10. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18.19 20, <hi>And Chriſt being a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedech, ver.</hi> 17. Then it will follow that they rob Chriſt, for robbing of his Miniſters is robbing of Chriſt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>will a man rob his Gods, yet yee have robbed me but ye ſay where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in have we robbed thee? in Tythes and Offerings.</hi> Now I hope,
<note place="margin">Act 9 4, 5.</note> they will not ſay that thoſe able and godly, and painful Miniſters which they have put into ſequeſtrations, and labor in the Word and Doctrine are not Chriſts Miniſters; and much leſſe affirme that thoſe ſcandalous and delinquent Miniſters, whom they have juſtly and orderly caſt out, are Chriſts Miniſters, and yet many Committees take from the one to give to the other; Is this juſt, to force Chriſts Miniſters to diſcharge the Office, and compel them to pay the fifth part of their maintenance, which Chriſt hath ordained for them, to the others, who neither rule well, nor labor in the Word and Doctrine? I trow, if a faithful Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Steward or Ambaſſador, ſhould be forced to pay a full fifth part of his pay or Salary to the Captains, Stewards, Ambaſſadors wife, or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166773:8"/>that hath been juſtly caſhiered, or diſplaced for inſufficiency, ſcandall or delinquency, he would not like it very well, but complaine and cry out injuſtice, njiuſtice, eſpecially if he ſhould be compelled to do the Office of a Captain, Steward or Ambaſſador, ſeeing <hi>omne benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium poſtulat officium.</hi> Every Benefice requireth the Office thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to belonging and <hi>omne officium beneficium poſtulat beneficium,</hi> Every Office requires the Benefice or Wages thereunto belonging? And what, is it Juſtice to compel the poor plundered Miniſter to performe all the Duties belonging to his Office, and yet force him to pay a fifth part of the Profits, Benefits or Wages thereunto belonging (whether hee can get them or not) to him or his, who perform not the Office, but is judged unable, or unfit to doe it?</p>
            <p n="4">4 That is not true ſpirituall mercy, which neceſſitates them to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their duty: But forcing of poor plundered Miniſters to pay fifth parts to the wives and children of ſequeſtred Miniſters, neceſſitates them to neglect their duty, even thoſe things which God himſelfe hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to doe, Therefore I conclude it is no ſpirituall mercy. The major is ſo clear, that I ſuppoſe, none will deny it. And the minor I prove thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It neceſſitates them to neglect their owne Families, their owne Wives and Children, for whom the Law of God and Nature requires them to provide for, <hi>He that provides not for his own family is worſe then an Infidel,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. for it is impoſſible for them to pay fifth parts and provide for their own Families, and do other duties too.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It compels them to neglect thoſe that are poor indeed, and ought to be releived, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.16. In which Chapter the Apoſtle diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth of two ſorts of Widowes. 1. Widowes that bee wanton. 2. Widowes that be godly and grave. And Widowes that are godly (widows indeed as the Apoſtle cals them) are of two ſorts. 1. Some are poor and without friends. And 2. Others have rich friends able to releive them. Now thoſe that are wanton muſt not be releived by the Church, nor thoſe that have rich friends, leſt it hinder the Church from releiving of thoſe widowes that are poor indeed:
<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</hi>
               </note> as ſtrong and ſturdy Beggars muſt not be releived (except in the caſe of extremity) leſt we do thereby rob thoſe that are aged, impotent, and unable to work, in the releiving of ſuch; Miniſters ought to go before others, not onely in Word and Doctrine, but alſo in Deed and Practiſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. But the Wives and Children of ſequeſtred Miniſters, are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166773:8"/>or never ſuch widows indeed, and fatherleſſe indeed, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would have releived by the Church (much leſſe onely by poore plundered Miniſters) though they are looked upon as ſuch, by ſome men that are better able to releive them then poor plundered Miniſters, and yet when they are ſuch indeed, they take no ſuch care, and pains to releive, but leave them to the wide world to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as godly Miniſters Wives and Children have done and doe) and why not now, as well as when their Husbands and Fathers are dead.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It hinders them from diſtributing to the neceſſities of the Saints and keeping of hoſpitality, both which they ought to do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. for fifth parts devoure the meat, drink, cloaths, and lodging, which would elſe be given to Chriſts hungry, thirſty, naked, and harborleſſe members, which mercy Chriſt accepts as done to himſelfe <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.35.40. Indeed they may bee given to hoſpitality, and other ſuch duties; but this forcing of them to pay fifth parts, makes them unable to perform them: for the neglect, or rather not doing of ſuch good works they are deeply charged by ſome men, with covetouſneſſe and unmercifulneſſe, and their names being thereby defamed, their perſons are ſoon deſpiſed, and their doctrine contemned, and God much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored. Is not the cauſe of the cauſe, the cauſe of the thing cauſed by that cauſe? And thus I hope I have ſufficiently proved, that forcing of poor plundered Miniſters (who labor in the word and doctrine) to pay fifth parts to ſequeſtred Miniſters Wives and Children, doth neceſſitate them to neglect, at leſt, leave thoſe things undone, which the Law of God commands them to doe: Therefore I conclude, that the forcing now, or lately in faſhion, of poor plunder Miniſters to pay fifth parts to ſequeſtred Miniſters Wives and Children, is not true ſpiritual mercy, eſpecially that intended by our Saviour in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.5. but rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſſe to thoſe poor Miniſters that have been plundered for their piety to God, and good affection to the Parliament, to their poore Wives and Children, to many hundreds of poor indeed; yea, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Jeſus Chriſt, who might and would be releived by godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters put into Sequeſtration (though they were kept out of, or under in the Miniſtery by thoſe unworthy men in the Biſhops time) were they not conſtrained to pay fifth parts to maintain Delinquents and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters their Wives and Children in pride, idleneſſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy—. For if they pay them not, they will either ſequeſter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166773:9"/>them, or impriſon them, or ſeize upon their Eſtates, ſometimes all three (there is no ſuch courſe taken to recover poor plundered Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters reall and juſt debts, which their people owe them for Tythes) or elſe they muſt leave laboring in the Word and Doctrine amongſt the people that have duely choſen them, and leave them to Dogs, Foxes, and Wolves to be devoured, which in conſcience they cannot do. Chriſt the great Shepherd, and Judge of all the world, ſeeth all theſe things, and will one day viſite for them all; But God give the Cauſers, Actors, and Abettors of them ſpeedy and unfeighned repentance for theſe and all other abuſings of his faithfull Meſſengers and Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>But you will ſay still, that Sequeſtrations have been freely given by the Parliament to many Miniſters, who had but little before Sequestrations were ſet on foot, and therefore met hinks they ſhould not be averſe from paying of that which they allow, and their Committees ordered to be paid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Sir, I doe not any way deſire to undervalue the Parliaments free bounty to any Godly Miniſters, much leſſe to them that have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to them in times of their extremity, and ſuffered for their ſakes, but honor them, and praiſe God that he did at firſt put it into their hearts to ſequeſter ſcandalous and delinquent Miniſters, and put godly and wel-affected Miniſters in their roomes: For by it much glory hath redounded to God, and good to his Church, themſelves, and the Commonwealth; I wiſh them well, and pray for them; but yet I cannot blame thoſe poor plundered Miniſters that ſtruggle as for life to be freed from that intollerable, and unlivelihooding bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of fifth parts, arbitrarily, and contrary to the Parliaments inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, impoſed on them by Committees, who compell them to make their full tale of Bricks, and yet make them borrow, yea, goe to law for ſtraw. I have heard ſo many ſad complaints by thoſe that are truly Godly and dare not lye, that I dare not condemn them, but as you ſee me thus pleading for them.</p>
            <p>But Sir, Your Object on I ſuppoſe is fully anſwered already, if all that hath been ſaid be well weighed, in the even Scales of unbyaſſed judgement. For though Patrons give Livings freely (as they ought to doe) yet if they impoſe or expect more from their Miniſters then is reaſonable and juſt, they muſt excuſe them, if they cannot comply with them. It is true indeed that many young men, who had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before the Wars, ſtood ſtill for a time, till they ſaw which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166773:9"/>way the ſcales would or did turn, have been freely preferred to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Places, and either they are not marryed, or but lately, and ſo have no charge, or but little, and have their Wives portions unſpent. Your argument might be ſomewhat to move them to a willing compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in what is juſt, and not prejudicial to their elder brethren; but many, yea, moſt of them dealt ſo warily as to refuſe ſuch Sequeſtrations as they thought were or would be cumbred with payment of fifth parts; but poor plundered Miniſters could not deale ſo circumſpectly; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plundered and having wives and children to maintain, and other plundered friends to releive, they could not pick and chuſe where and when they liſted, but were conſtrained through neceſſity to lay hold on that which was firſt offered, and therefore there cannot be in reaſon ſo much expected from them, as may be from ſome others, who loſt neither friends nor means, but have abundance, and no charge.</p>
            <p>But Sir, If your Argument were good, it would make that good Law againſt Symonie unjuſt, and lay open a wide gap for the admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lame, and the blind, and the unworthieſt of the people to enter into the great worke of the Miniſtery, as it was in the daies of <hi>Jeroboham</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of the Pope here in <hi>England.</hi> To prevent which inconveniencies, that neceſſary Law againſt Symonie was wiſely made by our Anceſtors, who though they had leſſe knowledge of God, yet had they more zeal for him and his Servants, then many of us, their degenerating poſterity have.</p>
            <p>Sir, You knowing the ſcantling of time I have had to anſwer your Queſtion, will (I hope) excuſe my plainneſſe, and pardon my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedneſſe, and whatſoever failings elſe may, upon ſerious peruſall, be found in this my indigeſted Anſwer. What I have done hath been to ſatisfie your deſire, and clear thoſe Godly Miniſters that lay under many hard thoughts, and bitter and heavy aſperſions, and move ſome compaſſion towards them, hoping that you and other godly men, will make what good uſe you can of all your intereſt both in Heaven and Earth, in and out of the Houſe, that thoſe poor Miniſters who have great charge of children, and have been plundered for their piety towards God, and faithfull ſerving the Parliament, may be abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged from that heavy burden of fifth parts and ſettled by Act of Parliament for their lives, where they have been placed by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Parliament; eſpecially ſeeing ſome of them, upon promiſe of many Parliament men, that they ſhould be ſettled for their lives, have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166773:10"/>left thoſe Places they formerly had, and have promiſed to ſtay with thoſe godly people that duely made choice of them, and have laid out much in repairing their old ruined Parſonage and Viccaridge houſes where they are, and alſo ſeeing if they are not both they, and their wives and children, and godly people will ſuffer many inconveniencies, and as bad put into the Miniſtery againe, as have been caſt out: By this means alſo, if others yet left in, ſhall be duly caſt out, young-men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into the Univerſities may be invited out, and chearfully goe on in the ſervice of God and the Commonwealth, in their Places and Callings. In conſidence of which, I ſubſcribe my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant. R. WILLIAMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166773:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Suppoſe that no honeſt man will move that thoſe that ſtand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred for ſcandall, may be admitted into the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry again, they being as ſalt that hath loſt its ſavor, are good for naught, but to be caſt out, as our Savior ſpeaks in <hi>Matth. 5.13.</hi> But as for thoſe that ſtand ſequestred only for Delinquency, and are not ſcandalous, but are able and Orthodox Preachers (they gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good ſecurity, that they will neither preach nor act any thing againſt the preſent Government, and be faithfull thereunto) I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (now the power of private Patrons is taken away) it will not be contrary to the rules of Chriſtian piety or policy, to give them liberty to labor in the Word and Doctrine, provided, it be not in any place where any godly wel-affected Miniſter is placed, nor near the place from whence they were ſequeſtred <hi>(England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are wide enough, and there will not be many) thereby both they and theirs will be better provided for then by fifth parts. But as for thoſe that are inſufficient, ſcandalous, or obſtinately Malignant, neither they nor their wives nor children have any right by the law of God to fifth parts, nor deſerve to have any ſuch releife by the Law of Man, but what is raiſed by way of tax as for other poor (if they be poor and unable to worke) or by free gift from their friends, but not by compulſion from the Parliaments poor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Miniſters, who labor in the Word and Doctrine, and therefore ſhould have the whole reward aſſigned for their maintenance and encouragement, to maintain themſelves and provide for their own Families, and performe ſuch other good works as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to doe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
